

# Tanyaradzwa Rodgers Ngara

Huazhong University of Science and Technology, 1037 Luoyu Rd, Wuhan, China

Personal Website

Google Scholar

rodgersn@hust.edu.cn

## **Profile**

A highly enthusiastic and motivated research scientist with a professional attitude who enjoys being part of a team and working to make it successful and productive. I grasp new ideas and concepts quickly and am innovative as well as creative in thinking up solutions to problems. I have demonstrated proficiency in conducting independent research, analyzing data, and presenting findings. I seek opportunities to utilize my knowledge and skills professionally to contribute to the scientific community.

## **Professional Summary**

The ultimate goal of my research is to study microbial communities' function, structure, and dynamics to understand their role in human health, biogeochemical and agricultural processes, and the environment. A comprehensive understanding of microbial communities' activities and dynamics holds promise for their exploitation in a wide range of challenges facing humanity today, such as enhancing crop production, biofuel and human medicine production, and environmental bioremediation. To achieve this goal, I have been pursuing interdisciplinary research and unifying the techniques from biotechnology, microbiology, metagenomics, molecular biology, droplet microfluidics, environmental sciences, and ecological risk assessment.

## Skills

Possess the technical skills and attributes necessary within a dynamic scientific research environment:

- Expertise in database development, data mining, and data analysis.
- Strong understanding of biodegradation processes and mechanisms.
- Experience in microfluidic device fabrication and droplet generation for single-cell assays.
- Ability to work independently and collaboratively in a team environment.
- Excellent communication and interpersonal skills, including experience in collaborating with interdisciplinary teams.
- Strong scientific writing and presentation skills, including peer-reviewed publications.
- Ability to work independently under challenging conditions with minimum supervision.
- Self-motivated and ambitious individual driven by the need to face new challenges.

#### **Education**

### **Huazhong University of Science and Technology**

Wuhan, China

09/2019 - Current

Ph.D.in Biomedical Engineering

- Academic advisor: Prof. Houjin Zhang
- Dissertation title: Development of Databases for the Biodegradation of Representative Pollutants in Wastewater

#### **Huazhong University of Science and Technology**

Wuhan, China

02/2017 - 01/2019

M.Eng. in Biomedical Engineering (Magna cum laude)

- Academic advisor: Prof. Houjin Zhang
- Thesis title: Design, Fabrication, and Characterization of Microfluidic Chips used for the Production of Monodisperse Double Emulsions

#### Chinhoyi University of Technology

Chinhoyi, Zimbabwe

08/2011 - 07/2015

BSc. in Biotechnology

- Academic advisors: Dr. Joice Ndlovu and Dr. Tawanda Chisango
- Thesis title: Identification and characterization of nitrogen-fixing bacteria isolated from root nodules of *Acacia tortilis* to enable the introduction of suitable and effective symbionts of legume crop plants

## Research Experience

#### Huazhong University of Science and Technology

Wuhan, China

Graduate Student Researcher

02/2017 - Present

Affiliation: Department of Biotechnology, College of Life Science and Technology and MOE Key Laboratory of Molecular Biophysics

#### Chinhoyi University of Technology

Chinhoyi, Zimbabwe

06/2014 - 06/2015

Research Assistant

Affiliation: School of Health Sciences and Technology

# **Work Experience**

#### **Huazhong University of Science and Technology**

Wuhan, China

09/2021 - 01/2022

Biology Teaching Assistant

- Collaborating with the professor: Working closely with the biology professor to develop lesson plans and ensure that course materials are up-to-date and relevant.
- Managing course materials, including updating and organizing lecture notes, laboratory manuals, and other instructional materials.
- Grading and providing feedback on assignments, quizzes, and exams.

Agri-biotech Pvt Ltd Harare, Zimbabwe

Agricultural Biotechnology Researcher

09/2015 - 01/2017

- Using biotechnology techniques to develop disease-free, drought-resistant, high-yielding varieties of traditional crops such as cassava.
- Experiments to attempt cotton Gossypium hirsutum L. regeneration via somatic embryogenesis.
- Regeneration and transformation of various crops, including maize, cotton, and potato.
- Identification and molecular characterization of the cassava mosaic brown streak virus coat protein

#### **Honor Awards**

#### **HUST Academic Excellence Award**

2022

Huazhong University of Science and Technology

#### **Publications**

- [3] **Ngara, T.R.**, Zeng, P., and Zhang, H. (2022). "mibPOPdb: An online database for microbial biodegradation of persistent organic pollutants", *iMeta*, 1(4), e45.
- [2] **Ngara, T.R.**, Zeng, P., and Zhang, H. (2022). "Biological Nitrogen Removal Database: A Manually Curated Data Resource", *Microorganisms*, 10(2), 431.
- [1] **Ngara, T.R.**, and Zhang, H. (2022). "Recent Advances in Function-based Metagenomic Screening", Genomics, Proteomics & Bioinformatics, 16(6), 405-415.

#### **Interests**

Volunteering and community involvement Reading History Listening to music

# Languages

English Shona Shona

Chinese

## References

Prof Houjin Zhang Dr Joice Ndlovu

Dr Nancy Muringai

Contact: nmuringai1@sheffield.ac.uk